Latin American mss.--Peru II, 1760-1820 LMC 1628
Lilly Library
Latin American mss.--Peru II
1760-1820
Lilly Library
LMC 1628
1 Box 1 standard
The Latin American mss. Peru II, ca. 1760-1820, consists of 25 documents which describe living conditions, roads, local Indians, etc. in Peru.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Historical Note
Until its conquest by the Spanish beginning in 1524, most of Peru was controlled by the Incan Empire. Spain then ruled the region as a colony until a rebellion, aided by military campaigns led by José de San Martín and Simón Bolívar, brought Peru's independence in 1824.
Scope and Content Note
The Latin American mss. Peru II, ca. 1760-1820, consists of 25 documents which describe living conditions, roads, local Indians, etc. in Peru.
Note on Indexing Term - "Law": There is a large quantity of legal material pertaining to Latin America in these collections. Royal and viceregal decrees, both de oficio and de parte, are especially numerous.
Note on Indexing Term - "Religion": A large quantity of this material relates to religious matters.
Note on Indexing Term - "West (U.S.)" and "Americana": There are items pertaining to early settlements and colonial government in Texas, California and New Mexico, and information on Texas independence.
Related Material
See Latin American mss.--Peru, also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: 1989
Peru--History--To 1820; International relations; Law; Religion; Americana; West (U.S.); Peru --Politics and government.
- Treasury documents, ca. 1653-1705 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Documents from and concerning the Real Hacienda in Lima, Peru.
- El alcalde pedanes[?]..., n.d. (Box 1)
- Exped.te promorrido por los Navieros r[?]esta Mar al[?] sur, 1810 (Box 1)
- A juste, de efectos, y prenda de Nestuario, pertenec. al primer Regim. de Infant.a de Qimea[?], 1815 (Box 1)
- Copiador de Cantas y Oficios..., 1790, Apr. 20-Sept. 21 (Box 1)
- El governador Yntend[en]te..., 1791 (Box 1)
- Sueldos militares, 3 Nov. 1819 (Box 1)
  Contains multiple documents and items of correspondence, including:
  Cover sheet reading "Sueldos militares"
  The first page of one document reads: "Los Navieros del Mar del Sur en el Expediente seguido sobre la indebida evaccion de un derecho que el R.l Tribunal del Cosulado de autoridad propia ha querido imponernos, y lo demas deducido decimos. Que a nuestra noticia ha llegado que el S.or Fiscal de S.M. con quien se sirbió V.E. substanciar nuestra representacion, ha opinado que tratandose de la declaracion e inteligencia de las Actas acordadas en Junta general de Comercio para el nuebo impuesto Patriotico, podria remitirse la instancia a la misma Junta, dando la orden oportuna para que se formase, y con su acuerdo, y Acta remitirse todo a Junta general de Tribunales a fin de que quede autorizada devidamente la contribucion que se determine, y deslindados todos los articulos de las referidas Actas. "Respetamos como es justo el dictamen, pero en defensa de nuestros derechos, hacemos presente a V.E. en primer lugar que no hemos imaginado poner la menor dificultad al cumplimento de lo acordado sobre la miela contribucion patriotica, ni al de los demas articulos de que se encargan las mencionadas Actas, cuya exacta obserbancia deseamos, y pedimos en la mexor forma Estimamos sobre manera, nuestra opinion, y concepto, d.[?] padecerian mucho justam. si hoy pretendiesema sin causa ni motibo libertarnos de una obligacion que hayer nos impusimos..."
  Correspondence on the topic appears to continue across multiple letters that follow this one
- Temp. chron. File, n.d. (Box 1)
- Augustinians. To Sanchez de Bada., 1738, Aug. 17 (Box 1)
- Delos Autos segundos..., 1761, Apr. 24-1762, Jan. 14 (Box 1)
- Es la Filiazion del casicasgo..., ca. 1775 (Box 1)
- Copia de las razones de los bienes de comunidad..., 1802, Jan. 9 (Box 1)
- Expediente sobre la lizencia..., 1821, Apr. 16-Nov. 25 (Box 1)
- González de Prada, Joseph (1761-1829), 1816-1817 (Box 1)
  Letters; some are written by Joseph Vicente González de Prada y Falcón Calvo, "Governador Intend[ien]te y Comand[ant]e General de las Armas y [?] entableados en la Frontera de la Prov[inci]a de Tarma"
- En días pasados..., 1823 (Box 1)
- Señor Vintn Gral..., n.d. (Box 1)